

PROFILE

I'm a molecular ecologist and research scientist with wide-ranging interests in animals, pathogens, and the use of DNA to detect and monitor them in relation to ecosystem health. I have diverse experience in research and consulting, and excel at data analysis and preparation of concise and clear reports and research manuscripts.

CONTACT

PHONE: 021 461 193

WEBSITE:

https://phoebeachapman.github.io

EMAIL:

phoebe.chapman@uq.net.au



@phoebeachapman



phoebeachapman

HOBBIES

Wildlife photography Tramping Skiing Bouldering/Rock climbing SCUBA diving

PHOEBE CHAPMAN

Research Fellow and Molecular Ecologist

EDUCATION

Curtin University 2017

Graduate Certificate with Distinction - Geographic Information Science

The University of Queensland 2017

Doctor of Philosophy (PhD) - Diversity, impacts and diagnosis of pathogenic parasites in sea turtles from Queensland, Australia

The University of Queensland 2004

Bachelor of Science (Hons) – Zoology and Marine Biology

WORK EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Research Fellow

University of Otago - Department of Marine Science

March 2024 - Present

Genomics-based research on various kelp, microbiome, and parasitology/diagnostics projects

Postdoctoral Research Fellow

University of Otago - Department of Zoology August 2020 – March 2024

Primary research fellow on RSNZ Marsden funded project investigating the role of microbes in *Xenopus laevis* tadpole tail regeneration

Senior Ecologist

JWA Ecological Consultants

2016 - 2020

Field assessment of flora and fauna, threatened species surveys, monitoring, management, ecosystem rehabilitation, reporting and impact assessment spanning a range of projects and development types in Queensland and New South Wales, Australia

Research Scholar and Teaching Assistant The University of Queensland - School of Veterinary Science

2012 - 2017

PhD scholar and concurrent teaching assistant contributing to undergraduate teaching in veterinary parasitology and One Health components of the Bachelor of Veterinary Science degree

Senior Ecologist

JWA Ecological Consultants

2007 - 2012

Research and Teaching Assistant

The University of Queensland - Department of Integrative Biology 2004 - 2005

Aquatic field surveys, data analysis and reporting, contracted by Brisbane City Council. Concurrent teaching assistant in undergraduate animal biology, marine ecology, and fisheries science.

AWARDS, GRANTS, SCHOLARSHIPS

	•
2022 & 2023	New Zealand Performance Based Research Fund (PBRF) NZD \$2500/year allocation
2017	Letter of Commendation (semester average > 90%) – Curtin University Dept. Spatial Sciences
2016	Uni of Queensland School of Veterinary Science Paper of the Week (three occasions)
2015	Best Oral Presentation (Wildlife theme) - Uni of Queensland School of Veterinary Science Research Conference (AUD \$500 prize)
2015	People's Choice Award - 3 Minute Thesis School of Veterinary Science Finals
2015	Uni of Queensland Advantage Sponsorship Grant (AUD \$3,000) (as part of Veterinary Science Postgraduate Association Committee) Uni of Queensland Graduate School International Travel Award (AUD \$3,855)
2012 - 2016	Australian Postgraduate Award Scholarship (approx. AUD \$90,000)
2002	Dean's Commendation for High Achievement –

SERVICE AND ADMINISTRATIVE ROLES	
2022 - 2024	Administrator Department of Zoology Twitter account, University of Otago (@zoology_otago)
2022	Panel Member Mason and Fairlea Prizes for best postgraduate paper in 2021 (Department of Zoology, University of Otago)
2019	Editorial Board - Review Editor Frontiers in Veterinary Science (Zoological Medicine)
2017 - 2019	Administrator School of Veterinary Science Vet- MARTI (Veterinary Marine Research, Training and

Uni of Queensland Science Faculty

2018 - Expert Panel Member Confirmation and Mid 2019 Candidature Milestone Reviews of PhD student Christabel Hannon

Investigation) Facebook page

- 2016 Journal Peer Reviewer Various international peer-2023 reviewed journals
- 2015 School academic recruitment selection panel Postgraduate representative School of Veterinary Science, University of Queensland
- 2015 Secretary Veterinary Science Postgraduate

 Association (VeSPA) Various roles including:
 Planning committees: Inaugural School of Vet
 Science Research Conference and Postgraduate
 Writing Retreat; Funding applications; Liaison and
 point of contact for school admin, staff and students

RELEVANT MEMBERSHIPS

Wildlife Disease Association Genetics Otago

OTHER QUALIFICATIONS AND TRAINING

- Quantitative Genetics short course Genetics Otago (March 13-16, 2023)
- Strategies and Techniques for Analysing Microbial Population Structures – Marine Biological Laboratory, Woods Hole, MA, USA (July – August 2022)
- Regression Methods in R Biostatistics Centre, University of Otago (Feb 2022)
- Bioinformatics Spring School Otago Carpentries & Genomics Otago (Oct 2021)
- R Programming Workshops University of Queensland (2014, 2015)
- Natural History Illustration certificate University of Newcastle (EdX - 2017)
- PADI Rescue Diver (Nitrox and Deep Certified 40 m)
- First Aid and CPR certificates
- Pony Club Association of Queensland Level C Instructor
- Wildlife Handling and First Aid (Wildcare Australia)
- Queensland Blue Card (Working with Children Check)
- Queensland White Card (Construction Site Safety)
- Queensland Recreational Marine Driver license (Boat) and Personal Watercraft license (Jetski)
- Queensland Marine Radio VHF/MF/HF Operators Certificate of Proficiency
- Queensland Driver License C Class manual (car) and New Zealand full driver licence (car)

STUDENT SUPERVISION

2022 Campbell Nicholas (BSc Honours)

Does TLR2 play a role in regeneration of

Xenopus laevis tails by binding bacterial lipopolysaccharides?

2017 Ida Ayu Dian Kusuma Dewi (MVSc) Detection of spirorchiid ova in blood samples from the green sea turtle (Chelonia mydas) by realtime polymerase chain reaction

2014 Kristen Nielson (BVSc 5th year research)
Molecular identification of spirorchiid parasites
and their potential hosts and pathological
effects on Hawaiian and Queensland green
sea turtles (Chelonia mydas)

PEER REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

Chapman PA, Hudson DT, Morgan XC, Beck CW (2024) The role of family and environment in determining the skin microbiome of captive aquatic frogs, *Xenopus laevis*. FEMS Microbiology Ecology 100(11) fiae131

Panthi, S., **Chapman, P. A.**, Szyszka, P., & Beck, C. W. (2023). Characterisation and automated quantification of induced seizure-related behaviours in *Xenopus laevis* tadpoles. Journal of Neurochemistry, 00, 1–11

Chapman, P.A., Gilbert, C.B., Devine, T.J., Hudson, D. T., Ward, J., Morgan, X.C. & Beck C.W. (2022). Manipulating the microbiome alters regenerative outcomes in *Xenopus laevis* tadpoles via lipopolysaccharide signalling. Wound Repair and Regeneration 30(6): 636-651

Hudson, D. T., **Chapman, P.A.**, Day, R.C., Morgan, X.C. & Beck C.W. (2021). Complete genome sequences of *Kinneretia* sp. XES5, *Shinella* sp. XGS7, and *Vogesella* sp. XCS3, isolated from *Xenopus laevis* skin. Microbiology Resource Announcements 10(50): e0105021

Cribb, T.H., **Chapman, P.A.**, Cutmore S.C., Huston, D.C. (2020). Pronocephaloid cercariae (Platyhelminthes: Trematoda) from gastropods of the Queensland coast, Australia. Journal of Helminthology 94: e105

Ban de Gouvea Pedroso, S., Phalen, D.N., Terkildsen, M., Blyde, D., March, D.T., Gordon, A.N., **Chapman**, **P.A.**, Mills, P.C. et al. (2020). Coccidiosis in green turtles (*Chelonia mydas*) in Australia: pathogenesis, spatial and temporal distribution and climate-related determinates of disease outbreaks. Journal of Wildlife Disease 56(2): 359-371

Stacy, B.A., **Chapman, P.A.**, Stockdale-Walden, H., Work, T.M., Dagenais J., Foley, A.M., Wideroff, M., Wellehan Jr, J.F.X. et al. (2019). *Caryospora*-like coccidia infecting green turtles (*Chelonia mydas*): an emerging disease with evidence of interoceanic dissemination. Frontiers in Veterinary Science 6: 372

Chapman, P.A., Cribb, T.H., Flint, M., Traub, R., Blair, D., Kyaw-Tanner, M., Mills, P.C. (2019). Spirorchiidiasis in

marine turtles: the current state of knowledge. Diseases of Aquatic Organisms 133(3): 217-245

Cribb, T.H., Cutmore, S.C., Stacy, B.A., Crespo-Picazo, J.L., **Chapman, P.A.**, García-Párraga, D. (2017). Elucidation of the first definitively identified life cycle for a marine turtle blood fluke (Trematoda: Spirorchiidae) enables informed control. International Journal for Parasitology 47(1): 61-67



Chapman, P.A., Owen, H., Traub, R., Flint, M., Soares Magalhaes, R.J., Kyaw-Tanner, M.T., Cribb, T.H., Mills P.C. (2017). Spirorchiid infection in green sea turtles (*Chelonia mydas*) in Queensland, Australia: a molecular investigation of epidemiology and pathology. International Journal for Parasitology: Parasites and Wildlife 6: 39-47.

Stacy, B.A., **Chapman, P.A.**, Foley, A.M., Greiner, E.C., Herbst, L.H., Bolten, A.B., Klein, P.A., Manire, C.A., Jacobson, E.R. (2017). Evidence of diversity, site and host specificity of sea turtle blood flukes (Digenea: Schistosomatoidea: Spirorchiidae): a molecular prospecting study. Journal of Parasitology 103(6): 756-767

Barton, D.P., **Chapman, P.A.**, Groom, R.A. (2016). Report of the presence of *Hapalotrema synorchis* and *H. postorchis* (Digenea: Spirorchiidae) in marine turtles (Reptilia: Cheloniidae) in Northern Territory waters. Northern Territory Naturalist 27: 78-83

Chapman, P.A., Traub, R., Kyaw-Tanner, M.T., Flint, M., Owen, H., Cribb, T.H., Mills P.C. (2016). Terminal restriction fragment length polymorphism for the identification of spirorchiid ova in tissues from the green sea turtle, *Chelonia mydas*. PLoS One 11(8): e0162114

Gillett, A., Ploeg, R., O'Donoghue, P., **Chapman, P.A.**, Webb, R., Flint, M., Mills P.C. (2016). Ultrastructural and molecular characterisation of an *Heterosporis*-like microsporidian in Australian sea snakes (Hydrophiinae). PLoS One 11 (3): e0150724

Chapman, P.A., Owen, H., Flint, M., Traub, R.J., Cribb, T.H., Mills P.C. (2016). Molecular characterization of coccidia associated with an epizootic in green sea turtles (*Chelonia mydas*) in south east Queensland, Australia. PLoS One 11(2): e0149962

Chapman, P.A., Cribb, T., Blair, D., Traub, R., Kyaw-Tanner, M., Flint, M., Mills, P.C. (2015). Molecular analysis of the genera *Hapalotrema* and *Learedius* (Digenea: Spirorchiidae) reveals potential cryptic species, with comments on the validity of the genus *Learedius*. Systematic Parasitology 90: 67–79

Chapman, P. and Warburton, K. (2006). Post-flood movements and population connectivity in gambusia (*Gambusia holbrooki*). Ecology of Freshwater Fish 15 (4): 357 – 365

NON-REFEREED ARTICLES AND REPORTS

Warburton, K. and **Chapman. P.** (2005). Fish and habitat surveys of Brisbane waterways 2000 – 2005. A report to Brisbane City Council.

Chapman, P. and Brooks, R. (2004). Rainbow rehabilitation: recreating waterways for native fishes. Wildlife Australia 41(2): 10-11

CONFERENCE PARTICIPATION

- 2024 Chapman, P.A. and Fraser, C.I. Scientific Committee for Antarctic Research XIth Open Science Conference Pucon, Chile.
 Investigating the dynamics of kelp-associated bacterial microbiomes in Antarctic and sub-Antarctic environments. Oral presentation
- 2019 Cribb, T.H., Chapman, P.A., Corner, R.D., Cutmore, S.C. Turtle Health and Rehabilitation Symposium – Gold Coast, AU. Spirorchiid flukes in marine turtles – how are they transmitted? Oral presentation
- 2016 Cribb, T.H., Cutmore, S.C., Stacy, B.A., Crespo-Picazo, J.L., Chapman, P.A., García-Párraga, D. 19th International Congress for Tropical Medicine and Malaria (inc. the Australian Society for Parasitology Annual Conference) Brisbane, AU. A lifecycle for a pathogenic marine turtle spirorchiid trematode. Oral presentation
- 2016 Chapman, P.A., Owen, H., Traub, R., Flint, M., Soares Magalhaes, R.J., Kyaw-Tanner, M.T., Cribb, T.H., Mills P.C. 19th International Congress for Tropical Medicine and Malaria (incorporating the Australian Society for Parasitology Annual Conference) Brisbane, AU. Terminal restriction fragment length polymorphism for identification of spirorchiid flukes in green sea turtle tissues: Application for investigations in disease epidemiology and pathology. Poster presentation
- 2016 Chapman, P.A., Owen, H., Flint, M., Traub, R.J., Cribb, T.H., Mills P.C. 19th International Congress for Tropical Medicine and Malaria (incorporating the Australian Society for Parasitology Annual Conference) Brisbane, AU. Coccidiosis causing mass mortality of wild green sea turtles in south east Queensland, Australia: Molecular investigations of an emerging disease. Oral presentation
- 2016 Session chair Aquatic parasitology stream 19th International Congress for Tropical Medicine and Malaria (incorporating the Australian Society for Parasitology Annual Conference) Brisbane, AU.
- 2015 Chapman, P.A., Owen, H., Flint, M., Traub, R.J., Cribb, T.H., Mills P.C. 1st Annual School of Veterinary Science Research Conference Gatton, AU. Molecular investigation of an epizootic event in green sea turtles associated with coccidiosis Oral presentation **Awarded Best Oral Presentation Wildlife Theme
- 2015 Ban de Gouvea Pedroso, S., Phalen, D.N., March, D., Blyde, D., Gordon, A., Chapman, P.A., Mills, P.C., Gillett, A., Lloyd, H., Roos, G., Hall, J., Scott.,

- J., Ariel., E., Rose., K. 64th Annual International Conference of the Wildlife Disease Association – Sunshine Coast, AU. Systemic coccidiosis in green turtles (Chelonia mydas) in Australia: An emerging infectious disease. **Oral presentation**
- 2015 Chapman, P.A., Traub, R., Cribb, T., Flint, M., Kyaw-Tanner, M., Blair, D., Mills, P.C. 64th Annual International Conference of the Wildlife Disease Association Sunshine Coast, AU. Molecular investigation and antemortem diagnosis of cardiovascular flukes (Digenea: Spirorchiidae) in marine turtles. Oral presentation
- 2014 Chapman, P.A., Traub, R., Cribb, T., Flint, M., Kyaw-Tanner, M., Blair, D., Mills, P.C. 45th
 Conference of the International Association for Aquatic Animal Medicine Gold Coast, AU.
 Characterisation and non-invasive molecular diagnosis of cardiovascular flukes from marine turtles in Queensland, Australia. Oral presentation
- 2013 Chapman, P.A., Cribb, T., Blair, D., Traub, R., Kyaw-Tanner, M., Flint, M., Mills, P.C. 24th International Conference of the World Association for the Advancement of Veterinary Parasitology Perth, AU. Morphological and molecular characterisation of cardiovascular flukes (Digenea: Spirorchiidae) from marine turtles in Moreton Bay, Queensland. Oral presentation

OTHER SPEAKING

- 2024 3rd Applied Microbial Ecology Laboratory
 Webinars: Exploring the ecology of the
 microbial world Universidad de La Frontera,
 Temuco Chile. Invited seminar Frogs, Fronds
 and Firmicutes Investigating the relationships
 between aquatic organisms and their
 microbiomes in the lab and in the sea
- 2024 MARI301 (Marine Ecology), University of Otago. Lecture – Introduction to eDNA
- 2022 GENE360 (Extension topics and Research Skills), University of Otago. Lecture postgraduate career pathways series
- 2016 Centre For Marine Science Seminar Series –
 University of Queensland. Pathogenic parasites
 from sea turtles of the Queensland coast.